This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
What I want to talk what what we were
talking about last time
was the density matrix description of
probabilities.
Now, the density matrix is another way
of speaking about the probability
um
probability postulate
and it's a situation which is more
general than knowing the state vector of
a system.
It's roughly speaking
when a system has been prepared but you
don't know how it's been been prepared.
And so, it may very well have been
prepared in a very definite state of
some sort.
I gave you an example last time
where an electron spin
might be prepared along a given along a
direction by placing the electron in a
strong magnetic field.
But somebody else did the preparing and
didn't tell you what direction the
magnetic field was in. Perhaps they gave
you a probability distribution for
different directions of the magnetic
field. Thank you for the coffee tonight.
I really need it. I hope this is coffee.
So, it's a situation where the system
does has been prepared
but you simply don't know how it was
prepared. Then how do you describe it?
It has to have a this has to be some
description.
You may have some degree of knowledge
about how it was prepared. You may have
none.
Incidentally, if you have none, if you
have no knowledge at all
then the density matrix has all equal
eigenvalues.
It's proportional to the unit matrix and
each eigenvalue is one over n where n is
total number of states. And that just
means complete random
uh information. You simply don't know.
All the possibilities are equally
weighted.
But let's just go back and discuss a
little bit more Well, not the the
review. The review
the basic uh equations and the basic
concepts that go with a density matrix.
The density matrix is the analog of
knowing the probability distribution for
classical states.
Classical states have some probability
distribution. In many contexts, you
would call it a probability density.
Density in phase space or a density in
coordinate space. A density of
probability.
That's where the word density matrix
came from and it's basically a a quantum
analog of the notion of a probability
density
or a probability distribution.
The
um condition that the sum of
probabilities adds up to one
is
denoted by saying the trace
of the density matrix is equal to one.
Remember, the trace is the sum of the
eigenvalues.
The eigenvalues themselves of the
density matrix can be thought of as the
probabilities
for different states.
So, first of all, the trace of the
density matrix
is equal to one.
The density matrix itself is a Hermitian
operator. That's basically just a
condition that the probabilities are
real.
Probabilities are real. So, in classical
physics, you would assign real
probabilities.
It's only somebody with a very bad
disorder would uh would assign them
uh complex probabilities. Wouldn't make
any sense.
The analog of that for quantum mechanics
is that the eigenvalues of the density
matrix are equal to one. Uh sorry. The
eigenvalues of a density matrix are
real.
Let's label them lambda i
where i is equal to
i equals 1 2 dot dot dot up to n where n
is the number of dimensions of the
vector space.
Um
Are they all positive, too? And they're
all positive. Good. And they're all
positive.
Right. Each
eigenvalue goes with some eigenstate.
Right?
And
in some basis
some particular basis of
in the space of states, some orthonormal
basis of states
uh corresponds to the eigenvectors.
Incidentally, remember that the
eigenvectors of a Hermitian operator are
all orthogonal to each other. So, they
form a basis.
So, there's some basis in the space of
states which is just uh
n mutually orthogonal vectors, each one
of them being an eigenvector and each
one having an eigenvalue lambda sub i.
You can simply think of the lambda sub
i's as the probabilities
that the system was prepared in the ith
eigenvector of the uh of the density
matrix.
If all the eigenvect- if all the
eigenvalues are equal it effectively
means you know nothing.
Uh you don't know what state the system
is in.
The density matrix then is proportional
to the unit matrix, all same
eigenvalues, each eigenvalue being one
over n.
That's one limit. That's the limit of
complete ignorance.
The limit of maximal knowledge
is a pure state. That means that you
know what state the system has been
created in.
Right?
In that case, we can say
the system is described by some pure
state. I won't tell you which one, but
let's say we assume we know which one.
Some pure state psi.
And when
the system is described by a pure state
there's still a density matrix. You can
still introduce a density matrix and the
density matrix is simply the projection
onto that pure state. The projection
operator that projects onto that pure
state.
in this way.
So, if there's only one state and
and you know which it is, it has
probability one for being in that state
then the density matrix is just psi psi.
How
How then how do I express that the the
state could be this one
with half of the ability and the other
half being some state 45° to it? Oh, no.
Um no no no no. That's not a good
concept.
The density matrix being a Hermitian
operator has a set of mutually
orthogonal eigenvectors.
And only makes sense to discuss the
probability for which state it's in in
that basis. In that basis. And so,
you'll be only situation you would talk
about. Now, we can we can answer the
question. Let me come back to it. Um
where
you don't know how the system was
prepared. Somebody may have prepared put
the magnetic field this way or may have
put it at 45°.
We can figure that out. We figure that
out later. I'll I'll come back to it.
But still, it will be the case that the
density matrix always has mutually
orthogonal eigenvalues. So, I will take
up that case either now or uh
Yeah, or next time. You mentioned pure
state.
You differentiate pure state from mixed
state? A mixed state means a density
matrix which simply has more than one
nonzero eigenvalue.
Yeah.
And uh yeah, it mean that's what it
means.
Okay. In German, it's called a gemisch.
It's the word I learned when I was a
young student.
Because German was still one of the
important languages of physics.
Now, it's just called a mixed state.
I think even by Germans.
And Germans?
Hm?
I'm just curious whether in German they
in Germany they call a mixed state a
mixed state.
I actually don't know.
Gemisch was the word that was invented
by the fathers of quantum mechanics.
What's that? It's a good German word,
gemisch. Gemisch, yeah.
Okay.
Now, what are the uh yes, let's just
point out one thing.
Take this matrix here. We'll take this
operator. It obviously has a single
eigenvector with eigenvalue one. What is
the eigenvector of this matrix with
eigenvalue one?
It's just psi, the same vector. If I
take this and operate on it let's assume
that now psi is is normalized. I assume
that it's normalized.
If I apply this to psi then psi psi is
equal to one. It just gives me back psi.
So, in fact, psi is an eigenvector with
eigenvalue one.
Uh
any other state orthogonal to psi
let's take some other state which is
orthogonal to psi
we call it phi.
If it's orthogonal to psi
then you get zero.
So, if the density matrix is a simple
projection operator onto one particular
state then it has one non-zero
eigenvalue.
The density matrix is representing a
pure state and the pure state is just
psi.
Now, whether or not the state is pure or
mixed,
the rule for average values
they usually called even in this case
expectation values. Uh,
I didn't want to confuse the terminol-
uh confuse the notation, so I just
indicated an average value.
Let's say the average value of the
observable M, which I'll indicate by
putting a bar over the top,
is just the trace.
I'll remind you in a moment what the
trace is.
The trace of
the density matrix times M.
And incidentally, it's not hard to prove
that a trace of a product of two
matrices, whether or not the matrices
commute,
whether or not
the trace doesn't matter which order you
put the uh
you put the um
uh the operators. So, you can also write
trace of M times rho and it will make no
difference.
That's the average.
Uh
and definition of the trace, let me
remind you the definition of the trace
of a matrix,
you take any base Excuse me.
You take any basis whatever.
The trace has the property that it
doesn't matter which basis you calculate
it in. It's an invariant under changes
of basis of the of the uh in the vector
space.
All right. But in any case, we take some
basis. It doesn't have to be the basis
in which rho is diagonal. It can be the
basis in which the rho is diagonal.
But
uh if even if it's not diagonal
in this basis, nevertheless, the trace
is defined as I
rho M, whatever the matrix in question
is, times I summed over I.
Okay. In other words, you just take the
I I'th matrix element of the operator in
question
and you sum it over all I.
That's the definition of the trace.
And let's work it out just for the very
simple case in which rho is a projection
operator.
In that case,
M is equal
trace. I'll write the trace in a moment.
psi
M
And now we take a complete basis,
whether or not I said it does not matter
whether the basis is the basis in which
rho is diagonal.
I
All right. So, now we have to do a
little bit of gymnastics. Oh, this is
summed over I.
If I forget to write sum over I, remind
me. It's almost always the case
that uh when you have
an index like I repeated twice,
almost in every equation I will ever
write down, it's implicit or I maybe
I'll I'll try to make it explicit. If I
forget, remind me.
But it's almost always the case that it
will be summed over so that I is really
just a summation index. Uh it's um
You call it J if you like. It doesn't
matter. All right. Let's check this out.
Let's see if this makes sense.
Um we can
rewrite this by just shifting this
factor over to this side. Let me do it.
All right. Let's rewrite it. I
psi M I
I
psi
Now, you have to remember the rule.
Whenever you see I and I back to back
like this summed over,
that's the unit matrix. That's the unit
operator.
The sum of I I
is the unit matrix. It can always be
canceled out. It's just the unit matrix.
It makes no difference. You can just
remove it and the result is that it's
psi M psi.
Well, that's not too surprising. The
average of M is the expectation value of
M if you have a pure state.
Now, supposing you don't have a pure
state,
let's suppose we don't have a pure
Question? Should that be M bar there?
Yeah. Uh this.
You have a bar on M. Oh, sorry. M bar up
here. Yes, thank you.
Very good.
Yep.
Okay. Let's uh let's take the more
general case when we don't have a pure
state
and
we'll see what we get. But let's
evaluate it. Let's see.
Um
Yeah.
Okay. So, again, we have to take trace
of rho M.
But let's do the calculation in the
basis in which rho is diagonal.
All right. So, to calculate the trace,
we put I
rho M
I
summed over I. I'm not going to write a
summation sign.
K-
uh
I'll suppress the summation sign for
now. Just summed over I.
But now we can insert a complete set of
states between rho and M. This is a
trick we constantly keep doing
uh in order to reduce the calculation to
a
something involving matrix elements of
both rho and M. We stick in between
there a complete set of states.
And we write it in the form I.
Maybe I I guess I'll I'll put the sum.
Sum on I
I
rho
M, but I'm going to insert in here a sum
over
J.
And now it's a sum over both I and J.
Now, if I'm working in the basis in
which rho is diagonal,
then I know what the ex- what the matrix
element I rho J is.
This is just the These I rho J, what is
that? That's just the matrix.
It has a I index and a J index.
The row or the column, let's see which
one is which. Um
This one is
uh
Whichever.
Yeah.
Um
J is the column, I think. Yeah.
Right. Okay. But since rho is diagonal,
this object here only has a matrix
element if I is equal to J.
And then the matrix element is just
lambda, lambda J.
The eigenvalue.
If
So, the sum over I and J becomes a sum
only over one of them and let's take it
to be J because I has to equal J because
rho is diagonal.
And then we have
J M J.
I've put J here because I has to equal J
in the sum.
Well, what is this? This is just the
expectation value of M in the J'th
state.
This is just the probability
of the J'th state.
So, this reads exactly what you might
expect. It's the average of M in the
J'th state
weighted with the probability, which is
the probability of the J'th state.
Okay.
So, you can think of the eigenvalues of
rho
as the probabilities to be in the J'th
state, but only in the basis in which
rho is diagonal. Yeah. Should that
really be J and J instead of J and I
there? Yes, because I has to be equal to
J, otherwise you don't get anything.
Right.
So, for trivial reasons it is.
You are still summing over I, right?
You're still summing over J here.
Over J.
Right.
Yeah. Here I really broke my own rule.
This thing is repeated three times.
Right.
Okay. Those are the rules about density
matrices.
Let me remind you of one more
definition.
If you're given a probability
distribution,
probabilities, let's say P sub I. This
is classical probabilities now. P sub I,
the I'th probability for the I'th
possibility,
then the entropy is defined
S, S for entropy.
I don't know why they chose S.
I don't know why it's not E. Probably E
because it would be confused with
energy.
Uh
S for entropy is equal by definition.
This is the definition of it. But we can
say what it means roughly.
It's again the sum over all of the of
the possible configurations or all of
the possible possibilities
of minus
P sub I times logarithm of P sub I.
That's its definition.
Again,
if only one of the P's is non-zero,
then it's got to be one.
All right?
Logarithm of one is zero.
On the other hand, all the other P's are
zero.
So, in that case, if you have complete
knowledge,
then the then the entropy is zero.
So, zero entropy means complete
knowledge. You know precisely that the
probability distribution is peaked at
one particular point, zero everywhere
else.
The other extreme is when you have
complete ignorance.
And in that case, um each piece of I is
one over N. Let's take it to be the same
N here.
Each piece of I is one over N.
And then you get S is equal to
before you do the sum, one over N, log
one over N, but it's minus log one over
N. So, that's actually the same as log
of N.
But then you have N terms in the sum.
So, you have to multiply this by N.
And the answer is that the entropy is
logarithm of the number of states.
The entropy is, roughly speaking, the
logarithm of the number of states which
are important in the probability
distribution.
That's as close as I can get to give you
a a definition in words.
But you don't need a definition in
words. This is precisely what it is.
But nevertheless, it is true that if you
have a probability distribution which
has fairly large over some set of
states,
and then pretty damn small everywhere
else,
that the answer for the entropy will
essentially be logarithm of the number
of states for which the probability
distribution is significant.
So, it's a measure of the
degree of ignorance. The more ignorance,
in other words, the more states that the
probability distribution is spread out
over,
the less you know about the system.
The more you know about the system, the
fewer the states, and the smaller the
entropy.
Okay, so it's measure of ignorance.
Or measure of well, yeah, that's
All right. Now, now we want to come to
entanglement.
Entanglement
happens when we have more than one
system.
So, let's suppose we have a a system
with a system composed of two parts.
And let's suppose we have some basis,
and the basis is labeled
by a state or a
an observable
A for one of the subsystems, and B for
the other.
Now, for the case of two spins, A and B
could be up and A and B could would both
be up and down. We can have up up, up
down, down up, down down. Okay?
Uh
other possibilities, we could have a
spin with two states,
and atom with four states or three
states.
Okay, in that case, A would go from one
to two or up and down. B would run over
one to three or one to four.
And so, altogether, the total number of
states
would be the product of the number of
configurations of the subsystem A times
the number of subsystem B.
So, if we had
a spin which could be in one of two
directions,
and we were putting it together with an
atom which could be in three possible
states, the total number of states would
be six. But it would just be three times
two.
Okay?
Let's um
let's say that A little A
runs from one
to capital N, and little B runs from one
to little N. They don't have to be the
same. They could be two quite different
systems.
Okay.
Then the most general state of the
combined system that we can write
is a sum.
And we're going to sum over A and B
of some
set of coefficients, called a wave
function
of A and B, function of A and B. Now, A
and B are discrete or at least for us
now,
A and B are discrete variables.
In a more general context,
A and B could might even be continuous,
but for our studies here, where we're
studying qubits and uh and discrete
systems, A and B
run over integers. They're inte- they're
integer-valued variables, but we can
still write psi of A and B, sticking in
any pair of integers that gives us a
complex number, multiplied by the state
vector AB, summed over A and B. That's
the most general state we can write
down.
If we want to normalize it, which I do,
then we want the sum over A and B of psi
star psi to add up to one.
Okay, so I won't write that down. The
sum over A and B of psi star
times psi should be equal to one.
And that's our normalization condition.
Okay, let's now suppose that we're doing
an experiment which does not involve B.
It could be because the two systems are
sub- are separated from each other,
and Bob is down at that end of the room.
He doesn't even look bother looking at
his system at all. Alice is up at this
end, and Alice is going to do an
experiment, and the experiment is going
to involve only the A degrees of
freedom.
Okay.
Uh
the observable that she's going to
measure, let's call it M.
M
is an observable
for subsystem
A.
That means mathematically
that when M acts on a state vector AB,
it may act on the A coordinate, but it
will just leave the B coordinate alone.
We've done this before. We've done this
with spins.
So, M effectively is only a matrix
in the A system here. It acts on the A
degree of freedom and leaves B alone. It
doesn't touch B.
So, whatever it does to a state vector,
B is completely passive and does
The matrix may act on the A coordinate,
and that's all.
So, that's a degree or a a variable,
sorry, an observable
that's associated with the A subsystem.
And let's calculate the expectation
value of it
in the state for the combined system.
So, what do we have to do?
We have to take First of all, we have to
take the bra vector associated with
this. Let's construct or rewrite it as a
the bra vector. Sum over A and B
psi star Well, let's see. We're going to
need two sets of variables. We're going
to need primed variables and unprimed
variables.
So, let's see how I did this. Yeah.
Psi star of A prime and B prime,
A prime B prime,
summed over A prime and B prime.
This is the bra vector.
Now, we're going to multiply that by M.
And now the ket vector, which looks
exactly the same Well, it looks exactly
the same except we won't have a complex
conjugate.
Psi of A and B,
AB.
I'll tell you what. Let's take the psi
and stick it on the outside here.
Now, we separately have to sum over A
prime and B prime to define the bra
vector, and A and B we also have to sum
over A and B to define the ket vector.
And that's the expectation value that
we're interested in.
But now, let's look at this matrix M.
M does nothing to B,
but it's a matrix as far as A goes. What
does that mean? That means that B prime
has to equal B.
Okay? B prime and B
The operator M does nothing to B. It
leaves it alone.
And if it leaves it alone,
then B prime and B must be the same.
Okay? Because
Let me ask you a question. Yeah.
You defined some of these variables
earlier.
Above, you didn't define psi of A and B.
There I used I and J.
No, but for the expectation of of rho M,
it's I
rho M I. No, okay.
Whoa.
We're not dealing at the moment with
density matrices. We're dealing with
state vectors.
So, let's go back and write an
expectation value for a state vector.
Okay? Supposing we have a wave function
psi of A times A single system
and now we want to calculate the
expectation and this is of course sum
over A.
Then the expectation value is M and now
we have to write the bra vector. That's
sum over A prime
of psi of A prime.
I know you do.
A prime.
Okay, so
in calculating the expectation value if
the vectors on either side are expressed
as sums, you have a double sum to do and
in this case and I've called the left
part of the double sum prime and the
right part unprimed.
Okay. So it's the same thing except we
have two labels here.
But now the definition of the idea that
M is an operator that acts on the A
subsystem and which is passive for the B
subsystem is simply the statement that
the matrix is diagonal in the B's.
That B on this side and B prime have to
be the same otherwise the matrix
vanishes.
In that case this double this sum over B
and B prime
becomes a sum only over one of them.
All right.
So let's let me show you what the the
right idea is now.
B and B prime have to be the same and M
is really just a matrix in the A space.
It's a matrix
with matrix elements A and A prime. Uh,
do I want to
I think I want to write it this way.
All right, this is a matrix
involving two variables A and A prime
but B has to equal B prime
and there's no dependence on B whatever.
No dependence on B and B has to equal B
prime.
Okay, so that's this matrix here
and all we have to do is remember the
instruction in the rest of the
expression here that B has to equal B
prime. So let's do that. Psi star
of A prime B
psi
of AB.
All right.
Notice on the left we have psi star of A
prime psi of A
but as far as B goes
B
Whoops.
B hasn't changed. B is just passive.
This is the Now let's go a little step
further. This is still summed over B.
It's also summed over A prime and A
but I want to ignore for the moment the
sum over A prime and A
and realize that this is a sum over B.
It's also a sum over A prime and A but
let's do that later.
All right.
All right. Now let me group
the two things that depend on B. Let me
group them together. So what I'm going
to do is erase this over here and I'm
going to put it back right back here.
Psi star of A prime and B.
All right. Now imagine holding A and A
prime fixed and just summing over B.
That gives you some expression here.
That expression no longer involves B
because B has been summed over. Once B
is summed over it doesn't depend on B.
Let's give this a name.
What should I call this? Psi of AB and
psi star of A prime B. It's a function
only of A and A prime.
I need a name for it.
Phi of A. No.
Phi of A A prime.
No.
Try again.
It's not the A and the A prime that I
don't like.
It's the phi.
Come on, give me the right letter.
Rho.
This expression
is the in in components, written in
components, written in terms of matrix
elements
is the trace of the product of M times
rho.
All right.
Why is it the trace? It's the trace
because I'm summing over A prime but
it's the product because I'm summing
over A.
This is the formula if I if I had
arbitrary things here, let's say A
double prime
then this would correspond to the A
double prime A prime matrix element of M
times rho. This is the way you multiply
matrices in terms of components.
This expression is
trace
of M times rho.
Let's check that. Let's do it by
longhand calculation that really is the
trace.
Now we're talking about a system. We're
only talking about the A system now.
We've eliminated the B system. We've
summed over it. It's no longer even in
this expression. This might have been
something that made sense for just the
pure A system without any reference to B
at all.
What would it correspond to? So let's
forget B.
It's passive. It's gone. Uh, we finished
with it and this is some expression only
involving the A degrees of freedom. All
right.
I assert that it's the trace of the
matrix M. Now remember M really only
depends on A and A prime.
B is completely passive. B prime has to
equal B and otherwise it just doesn't
depend on B.
So It's the identity on B.
Uh, M is the identity on B. Yeah.
Yeah, right. Uh, acting on B it does
nothing.
Right.
Okay, so let's let's just calculate
trace of M. We can write it as A prime
M
rho A prime summed over A prime. All of
this is summed over A and A prime. A and
A prime.
Okay. Back we have to sum it.
All right, this is the trace. This is
the definition of the trace.
But now if I insert a complete set of
states in here it becomes sum over A and
A prime of A prime
M A
A rho A prime. That's just this.
M A A A prime A, that's this
and rho A A prime.
That's this.
All right, so look what we found.
We found that by ignoring B
just ignoring it and asking what are the
rules
when a system is a combined system with
a unique state vector, a pure vector, a
pure it's a pure state for the combined
system
nevertheless
when you focus only on the A subsystem
it's described by a density matrix.
That density matrix, how do you get the
density matrix? You get the density
matrix by taking the full wave function
letting A and A prime run freely, not
summing over them but summing over B.
That eliminates B out of the expression
and it just becomes a matrix between A
and A prime.
So when you have a combined composite
system
Schrodinger's cat and the gun
All right.
The the Schrodinger's cat and the gun
may themselves be described by a single
state vector in which they're
entangled but if we just look at the cat
alone, the cat is described by a density
matrix. It's described by a density
matrix and in general that density
matrix will be a density matrix of a
mixed state in general.
There's a very special circumstance
under which it will be a pure state that
will describe the A system and I'll tell
you in a moment what it is.
In fact
I suppose I should tell you right now.
Any questions up till now? Yeah.
Isn't trace of M rho just trace of M?
Why?
Trace of M rho is the trace of M times
trace of rho and trace of rho Wait,
wait. Trace of No, sorry. Trace of
product is not the product of traces.
No.
It'd be nice if it were, make things
easy but it's not true.
Trace Trace of a product is not the
product of the traces, yeah.
You said you started with a pure state
which was just AB.
No, no, no, no. Psi. No, no, not AB but
sum over AB of psi A.
Okay, so you're not dealing with This is
the most general case that you can This
is the most general pure state of the
combined system. Okay, so let me say it
again. You have a combined system. It's
in the purest possible state. Sorry.
When you look at a subsystem, the
subsystem will be in a mixed state in a
statistical state. Now there's no analog
of this for a classical system.
If I have what would correspond to a
pure state for a classical system
for for a classical system the idea of a
pure state would be a probability
distribution which has only one point
that it's non-zero. In other words, a
definite piece of information about
which state you're in.
That's the analog of the pure state. In
other words, complete knowledge. If you
have complete knowledge about the
combined system, you have complete
knowledge about either of the subsystems
in classical physics.
So, in classical physics
complete knowledge about a combined
system is equal
it's not equal to, but it implies
complete knowledge about either of the
subsystems.
That's different in quantum mechanics.
In quantum mechanics, you may have
complete knowledge about the combined
system, and yet the
subsystem by itself must be described by
a density matrix.
Now,
you say, might it be that that density
matrix is special
and that it combine corresponds to a
pure state?
Not in general, and I'll show you some
examples. I'll show you some examples
that already are familiar with.
Uh we'll work out the density matrix for
some familiar example.
But, let me just say young.
How different is this from in classical
mechanics where you have velocity
distribution functions
which you integrate over to get
densities?
So, in a way
in a way you integrated over the B state
Yeah. to get a density matrix, right?
Yes.
So, I can think of
a velocity distribution function if you
integrate it over, you get the density.
How do I get a density by integrating
over Oh, you mean if you have
a combined velocity and position uh In a
classical probability distribution
function like a Boltzmann. Uh you have a
combined velocity and
uh and position distribution and you
integrate It's it's it's similar. It's
similar.
But,
difference is that if you had complete
knowledge In that case,
the velocity and the position would just
correspond to two subsystems. They're
not really two subsystems, but you could
think of them as two different systems,
two different coordinates uh that uh
Okay. In that case, if you had complete
knowledge about the system, it would
mean you knew both the velocity and the
position.
And there's no problem with knowing the
velocity and the position.
And so, not only would the combined
system be in a pure state, but if you
just looked at positions, you would have
definite knowledge of position and
definite knowledge of um
What's it all the thing called?
Velocity. Yeah.
Okay, so that's the difference.
That that there are pure states of the
combined system which cannot be thought
of as pure states of the subsystems.
Okay, let's me just tell you what is the
condition. All right, so here's an
interesting condition. What is the
condition on psi of A and B that the
individual subsystems actually are in
pure states?
Is there a situation
or a wave function psi of A and B in
which the two individual subsystems are
in a pure state?
The answer is yes.
Anytime
that the wave function factorizes into a
product of A, a product of a function of
A, and a product of a function of B.
Let's just analyze that that situation a
little bit
and see what it says. It's a special
case. Not all functions of two variables
are products of functions of one
variable times a function of another
variable.
But, it's only when the wave function is
a product that each individual subsystem
is itself in a pure state.
Okay, let's look at that a little more
carefully.
Let's suppose that psi of A and B
happened to be equal to a product of a
function of A
and another function of B, and I'm going
to call the other function chi of B.
Really, all this is saying is that the
combined system is a pure state phi for
the A subsystem and a pure state chi for
the B subsystem.
We'll assume that phi and chi are
normalized
so that chi star chi when summed over B
is equal to 1, phi star phi when summed
over A is equal to 1. Those conditions
are equivalent to the to the
normalization of psi itself. So, phi is
phi of A, that's only some of the of the
A
cats.
Well, it it's
Functions aren't composed of cats, but
yes, in that sense, right. Yeah, yeah, I
know what you
It's a linear combination of all of the
A cats.
Yeah, that's right. That's right.
It's a product state, right.
Right. It's a product state. Okay. So,
if phi happens to factorize like that,
then let's calculate the density matrix
itself.
The density matrix for the A subsystem.
All right. For the A subsystem, we have
to multiply psi of A and B times psi
star
uh
You know something?
I think I actually have something
backwards. No, it's all right.
Okay, um
So, we have to take psi of A and B times
psi star of A and B.
That's phi of A chi of B
times
phi star of A prime.
We have A and A prime, but B goes with
B.
times chi of B.
chi star of B.
Summed over B.
That's the density matrix rho A A prime.
All right, same formula except I've
substituted for psi the product.
All right, now this is very easy.
Um the only thing that's summed over is
chi.
A isn't even in the sum. You can pull
the phis outside the summation since the
summation doesn't involve A altogether,
and it just becomes equal to phi of A
phi star of A
times
sum on B
of chi of B times chi star of B.
But, what is that? Sum on B chi chi
star, that's just 1.
That's the normalization of chi of B.
So, this is all just 1.
So, the density matrix for a product is
very simple.
It's just
a product of wave functions
phi of A
times phi star of A.
Let's calculate now in this case the
expectation value of M.
It's just equal. Where is it? M of A
prime and A.
Sorry, I missed a prime here somewheres.
Right.
It's M of
A prime and A
phi of A, and let me put phi star
of A prime over here.
Well, this is nothing but written in
components,
this is nothing but
phi
M phi.
In other words, the expectation value of
M, and not just M, but any observable
that involves only A is exactly the same
as if the state vector were just phi.
The
A degrees of freedom are completely and
entirely described by the pure state
phi.
So, when the wave function is a product
of two factors,
each subsystem is itself in a pure
state, and the pure state is just either
phi of A or chi of B.
That's the special case when the
combined system is in a pure state and
each subsystem is in a pure state.
But, that's hardly general.
Not at all general. Not every function
of two variables is a product
of functions of one variable.
Okay. Incidentally,
in this case, the density matrix
Well, here is the density matrix.
The density matrix has one and only one
non-zero eigen vector.
It's phi itself.
All the other
eigen values are equal to zero,
and the entropy is equal to zero.
Only eigen values are one, and all the
others are zero.
So, that's the case. That's
one way of diagnosing how pure a state
vector is, or how well
the the wave function resembles a
product, is to calculate the entropy. If
the entropy is small, it means you're
near the situation of a pure of a of a
product.
If the entropy is large, somewheres near
the maximum logarithm of N, that means
you're deeply entangled. And deeply
entangled means you're far from a
product.
Far from a product, wave function just
doesn't factorize.
Let's work out
one particular example.
Maybe we can work out some more than one
particular example, but let's do at
least one example
with familiar thing that we've already
studied.
Calculate the density matrix and
calculate the um
uh the
the entropy.
We should do two. We should make one
We're going to do two different
examples.
The first example is not going to be a
pure state. The first example is going
to be our friend the singlet state, the
highly entangled singlet state of two
electrons. Okay. So, what is it? It's by
definition up up No, sorry. Up down
minus down up
divided by square root of two.
Right?
But, let's write that in terms of a wave
function of two variables.
Psi
has two entries. The first entry
represents spin number one, the second
entry represents spin number two. And
here are the values that psi has.
Psi up up is equal to zero. I don't see
up up here. Do you? No.
Okay. What about psi up down?
That's the coefficient of this one. It's
equal to one over square root of two.
How about psi down up?
Minus one over square root of two.
And psi down down
is zero.
Okay, let's calculate the density matrix
for the A system, the A system now being
spin number one.
So, what do we have to do? We have to
write down Where is it?
This is the density matrix right here.
I had it somewhere as yeah, that's
No, it's over here.
This is the density matrix summed over
B.
Summed over B.
All right. So, we begin by writing down
psi next to a psi star. Let's work it
out.
Let's Yeah, which Let's do the elements.
Row
up up.
Remember, row is a matrix, but it's a
matrix just in the space of one spin.
So, let's calculate its up up and matrix
element. This up up matrix element we
get by writing psi up
Let's write it again. Psi up.
Plus
This doesn't make sense yet. It will in
a moment.
Okay.
All right. Now, remember we sum over the
B coordinate. So, let's put up
up
down No, no. This is uh
Up up up up.
We're calculating the up up matrix
element. All right. Let's come back to
here.
We're calculating the A A prime matrix
element. So, in one place we put a psi
with an A, in the other place we put a
psi star with an A prime. This should be
star.
Star.
In this case, both A and A prime are up.
So, we have a psi of A and a psi star of
A a psi of A and a psi star of A, but we
have to sum over B.
So, B is up up and down down.
That's the instruction. It's psi star
psi
with the A's being evaluated
as matrix elements of the density matrix
and the B's being summed over.
Up up
plus down down.
Okay, that's the up up matrix element.
Let's see what it is.
Psi up up is zero.
So, this is zero, but psi up down is one
over square root of two.
So, this is just one half.
All right. What about row down down?
For row down down, you do exactly the
same thing. Psi down, psi star down.
Plus same thing. Psi down
psi star down Sorry. Psi star down.
But, then you fill in
up up
down down.
Do I have this right?
Yeah.
Okay.
What is psi down up?
It's minus one over square root of two.
It's squared. So, again we get one half.
And down down is zero and down down is
zero.
So, this is again a half.
Neat.
What about psi up uh row up down?
The matrix element of the density
matrix, the up down matrix element. Do
the same thing.
Psi up
psi star down
up down up down plus write it again
psi up
psi star
down
but then fill in
up up
and down down.
Okay, what's that?
Zero.
Psi up up is zero and psi down down is
equal to zero.
So, that's zero.
And of course, the other one is also
zero. Row down up is also equal to zero.
So, in this case, the density matrix
is just equal to row is equal to a half
a half.
It's proportional to the unit matrix. It
has equal entries.
Those entries can be thought of as
probabilities if you like.
But
its trace is one.
If you add up the eigen values, it adds
up to one.
And what's the And what's the um the
entropy?
No.
Two.
Log two.
It's one half log of one half
plus log one half log of one half. All
together it adds up to log of one half.
Log of one half is minus the log of two,
but we have a minus sign in the
definition of the entropy.
So, it's log two. That's the maximum
that the entropy can be. I haven't I
haven't stressed this.
But, it's an easy theorem.
Uh you might want to try to work that
out. That the maximum the entropy ever
can be is when all the elements of the
density matrix are equal. Maximum amount
of ignorance.
And so, in this case here, we have a
pure state
for the combined system and complete
ignorance for either of the uh
for either of the components. Uh sorry,
for either of the spins. I concentrated
on the left spin here, spin number one.
And what we found is that the density
matrix described complete ignorance.
In this case, what is the expectation
of the components of the spin, in
particular spin number one?
All right.
We could calculate them by using the
full wave function here, or we can
calculate them using the density matrix.
The density matrix for spin number one,
row
is equal to one half times the unit
matrix. We can just call it one half.
It's just one half times a unit matrix.
The expectation value of any component
of spin
spin along any axis
spin along any axis is equal to the
trace of row
times Sorry. Just sigma dot n.
Sigma dot n.
Trace of row
sigma dot n
That's the average.
The average of sigma dot n.
Trace of row times the observable.
That is not trace of row.
Not the observable times trace of row,
but trace of the product of row times
the observable. That's the average of
the observable.
Well
row is proportional to the unit matrix.
You can take that out. Unit matrix
doesn't do anything.
It just uh it just gives you a half,
factor of a half.
Just gives you a half times the trace of
sigma dot n.
What's the trace of sigma dot sigma dot
n? Anybody know?
Zero.
The trace of every one of the sigma
matrices is zero. Let's just check that.
Trace of sigma three
sigma three is one minus one.
Its trace is zero.
The others are all off diagonal.
They also have no trace.
So, what have we learned?
We've learned that in
the singlet state It's something we
already knew because we'd already worked
it out. That in the singlet state, the
trace of every component of spin in any
direction is zero, which means in any
direction whatever the spin is equally
likely to be along that direction or
opposite to that direction.
We already knew this.
And this was an example of a highly
entangled state. We also know that for
no pure state of a single spin
is the average of the spin equal to zero
in every direction. So, this is another
way of seeing that that this cannot be a
pure state.
But, the easy way to see that it's not a
pure state is that the two eigenvalues
here are both non-zero. So, it has to be
a mixed state.
So, the singlet state is a maximally
mixed state.
Let me take another one.
Uh
let's
Let's uh
Let's try the following. Let's see. Up
up um
uh
I think I want one over the square root
of two here. Let me just
Or do I want one half? Wait.
Um
I think I want one half.
Yeah.
Yeah, sure I do.
One half and one half.
Yeah, now it's normalized, right? I have
four
psi star psi would give a quarter. A
quarter plus a quarter plus a quarter
plus a quarter, no minus, plus
would give one. So, this is a normalized
state with all entries equal to a half.
Let's recalculate what we would get here
if we had this situation. This is not
the singlet state.
All right. So, now what do we have? We
have up up equals a half.
So, this is a quarter, right?
Is that right?
Right.
And this is also a quarter.
Quarter plus a quarter is again a half.
No difference.
All right. So, this is still a
a half. This one is still a half, but so
is this one.
All the matrix elements are equal to a
half. So, it's a half times a half plus
a half times a half. They're all equal
to a half this time.
And in fact, this one is also equal to a
half.
Now, this is the density matrix.
Its trace is still equal to
one. That's good. Sums of the
probabilities are equal to one.
But, what are the two eigenvalues of
this matrix? Are they equal?
No, actually they're not. Let me show
you what the two eigenvalues are.
Let's calculate the two eigenvalues.
Incidentally, do you know the theorem
that says that the product of the
eigenvalues of a matrix is equal to its
determinant?
That's one way to do it. That's one way
to check the eigenvalues here.
Good. Let's use that Let's use that
fact. This is a fact.
The product of the eigenvalues of a
matrix is equal to its determinant.
And the sum of the eigenvalues is equal
to its trace.
So, we now know the sum of the two
eigenvalues of this matrix
are equal to one.
That's good.
The sum of the eigenvalues is equal to
one. What about the What about the
determinant of row?
Right.
It's a half times a half minus a half
times a half.
So, the product of the eigenvalues adds
up to
zero. That means one of the eigenvalues
is zero and one of the eigenvalues is
one.
What's that?
Yeah, this is a product state.
This is a product state. Can anybody
guess what it what it corresponds to?
It's what?
It's two unentangled electrons, but what
are the individual electrons doing?
Uh yeah, they happen to be measured the
same way, but which direction?
In what direction? Well, along what
axis?
X.
Okay.
Let's calculate the expectation value
of um
Let's start with the expectation value
of sigma of sigma Z. Let's start with
sigma three.
All right. So, for that we take the
trace of row
times sigma three.
Let's see what we get.
Sigma three, and it doesn't matter which
order.
Sigma three is one minus one zero zero.
And row is one half one half
one half one half.
Okay, let's see what the product is.
One times one half plus zero times this.
This is equal to a half.
Uh one times a half is a half is a half.
Zero times a half is a half. A half.
And now
minus a half minus a half.
Now, I have to take the trace of it.
Trace is zero. So, the expectation value
of sigma three is again zero.
The same will be true of sigma two, but
let's calculate the trace of the product
row times sigma one now.
Let's put sigma one there.
Let's see what we get.
Sigma one was the matrix one zero one
one zero zero.
Okay. So, on the top row times the first
column, we get a half.
Same thing over here.
Oh, looks like we get a half here also.
Now, we get
Same thing. Everybody's a half, right?
And the trace is equal to one.
So, the expectation value of sigma one
is one.
The expectation value of the other
sigmas is zero.
This is a spin This is a pair of spins
that happen to both be lying along
the x-axis. It's a product.
Its entropy is zero because it has one
zero eigenvalue and one eigenvalue equal
to one.
All right. So, if somebody gave you this
density matrix here and said
tell me, is it a pure state?
All you have to do is calculate its
eigenvalues and calculate its entropy.
Or if they ask you, how pure is it? You
could characterize it by its entropy. In
this case, the entropy is zero.
If you change these numbers a little
bit, for example, make this instead of
one half, make it point four.
And make this one point four or
something like that.
Uh you'll change things a little bit.
And instead of finding a zero
um entropy
density matrix, it will have a small
amount of entropy.
In other words, there'll be a small
degree of entanglement.
So,
entropy, entanglement
go together.
And uh it's sometimes called the entropy
that one gets this way because systems
are entangled is called entangle
entanglement entropy.
Okay, let's take a little break.
First of all, in the cases which we've
been doing,
we've assumed that the combined system
is in a pure state. The combined
composite system has
a definite wave function. That means the
combined system
should be thought of as having a pure
state. Right?
As far as the combined system goes, that
means that its entropy is zero. There's
no uncertainty in the wave
function or in the state vector of the
combined system. It has zero entropy.
The entropy that we're talking about
The subsystem now, which we're looking
at, which is subsystem A,
by virtue of the fact that it's
entangled with B,
A has an entropy.
If you didn't look at B, A has an
entropy.
Notice one thing, and this is a general
property
uh of uh of this kind of entanglement
entropy or this kind of entropy. It
doesn't add.
The combined system has zero entropy.
The two subsystems each have As a matter
of fact, would have entropy of logarithm
of two in the singlet state.
All right. So, entropy in general does
not add.
So, under special circumstances, it may
add, but in general, entropy is not an
additive quantity. In particular,
entanglement entropy is not
uh an additive thing
because the typical situation
will be that the combined system is a
pure state, zero entropy, the two
subsystems each will have some positive
entropy.
Okay.
So, we have to distinguish between the
entropy of the subsystem and the entropy
of the composite system.
And as I said, I'll say it once more, it
is not additive.
I I I think it's probably fair to say it
really is always entanglement entropy,
but sometimes it's a little bit obscure
what's what's entangled with what.
Um
But, you know, if you count the the
magnets and the people who have prepared
the system and so forth,
uh then the only reason there would be
for not knowing
which way
a spin was prepared would be that uh the
preparation was entangled with the
thoughts of the preparer or something.
But, if we want to keep uh if we want to
keep the observer out of it, we would
just say that
uh that there's different probabilities.
That's one origin of uh of um of a
density matrix.
But, the other origin is entanglement. I
suspect probably entanglement covers
them all, but then you would have to
think about entanglement with what and
uh
and it could they can get complicated.
All right. Um I want to leave the
subject of entanglement for a while. I'm
pretty sure we'll come back to it.
But, there's one thing we haven't talked
about at all.
It's how it's how states change with
time.
In classical physics,
in classical logic and
if we're dealing with a discrete system,
if we're dealing with a discrete system
with a set of
with the configuration space being a
system of points,
could be just two points, heads or
tails,
the only kind of evolution that makes
sense is discrete evolution, where time
occurs in steps and at each step the
system moves from one state vector to
not state vector, from one configuration
to another configuration.
And you could simply represent
the evolution by a permutation.
If you start in this vector Sorry, I
keep saying vector. If you start with
this state,
you go to here,
and then you go to here, and then you go
to here,
you go to here,
here,
here, and perhaps back to here.
That would define the evolution of a
system. Just a a permutation which tells
you where every state
goes.
Uh it doesn't have to be all connected
like this. You could have four states
and the rule could be this one goes to
this one, this one goes to this one,
this one goes to this one, this one goes
to this one. That's also okay.
Why why it has to be discrete time?
Well, because how are you going to go
from one discrete state to another
discrete state continuously?
How are you going to go from heads to
tails? Well, you could turn it over
slowly,
but no no no, but that would mean that
there were intermediate configurations.
That wouldn't really be a two
configuration system.
Yeah.
If there are discrete configurations,
then I think you would have to say that
you have to that evolution would occur
in discrete steps.
In quantum mechanics, in some sense, you
can have Well, we certainly have systems
which are discrete, a finite number of
orthonormal states,
but
uh the evolution of a system can be
continuous.
Then why is that? You can have Well, why
is that? You can continuously go
from up
to down.
Up means a magnetic field pointing along
the up axis has locked the electron into
place.
Down means the electron has been locked
into place by a down magnet. And of
course, you have an infinite uh
continuous number of possibilities in
between.
So, although there's only two measurable
possibilities for the up spin,
so in that sense, the system is
discrete, nevertheless, you can
continuously interpolate between them.
Uh and so that allows the possibility
then that state vectors can vary
continuously with time even for a system
which
uh is discrete in the sense that the
dimension of the vector space is finite.
Let's um
Let's talk about how state vectors
change with time.
Now, there's an assumption.
And the assumption, the basic
assumption, is that the logical
relationships between states
doesn't change with time. For example,
if you start with two states which are
the same state,
then and allow the system to evolve,
of course, the two states will evolve
into the same state. That's trivial. You
start uh you start
You start with a particular state and
you let it evolve, it evolves into some
definite state.
What about if there are two states of
the system which are orthogonal to each
other?
Spin up and spin down.
Well, the assumption is that two
orthogonal states of the same system, if
you allow them to evolve, would evolve
into two orthogonal states.
That the distinctions, the fact that
they're measurably different, will be
preserved with time.
You could imagine In- incidentally,
that's uh that's also true in the
classical description,
that
you don't have the situation where two
different states could evolve to the
same state. That never happens in
classical physics.
You would lose memory then.
And then maybe you go to here.
Starting here, you could go to here, and
maybe from here you go back to here.
Well, then you would lose memory of
whether you started here or here,
because whether you start here or here,
you wind up here.
That doesn't happen in classical
physics.
There's never a loss of memory of where
you were.
So, I was thinking bifurcation
or non-linear analysis, essentially you
do have multiple steady states.
Not at the microscopic level.
Right.
This is a principle of physics. In
classical physics, it's called
conservation of phase space volume.
That the phase space volume stays the
same, never contracts or expands.
But uh
in quantum mechanics, it has another
name. The other name is unitarity.
But, what it says
is that the inner products between two
states stay the same with time. If two
things are orthogonal, they will remain
orthogonal. Each state will change in
its own way,
but
if state number one is and state number
two are allowed to evolve with time,
they will remain orthogonal. So, for
example, if you start with a spin up,
and you put it into some magnetic field
that could be doing complicated things,
after a while, the state will change
with time.
If you started with a state down,
after a while, it will change and become
some other state, but the two final
states will remain orthogonal to each
other.
All right. So, the principle
Is that only if they're under the
exactly the same influence?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Under the same
influence. Right. Right. Yes,
absolutely. Yeah. This is facing
obvious, but so
if one spins up and one spins down on
the Z axis with a magnetic field lying
along X axis, Yeah.
Yeah. What will happen
What will happen is if you put it into a
magnetic field along the X axis, and you
start with either a spin up or down,
they will begin to process. They will
rotate. All right? So, they might rotate
after half a period or something to one
being along this axis, the other being
along this axis.
But, those are orthogonal to each other.
Okay? So, orthogonality is maintained
with time.
Even stronger,
inner product is remain is is
um
inner product between two vectors
is time independent. So, let's
Actually, I should say that's the second
principle of time evolution.
The first principle of time evolution
is that it's governed by a linear
operator.
Let's start with the first principle
first.
Start with any state psi. It could be
any state of the system.
And let's
imagine it at time zero.
Okay?
After a certain amount of time, it
evolves to a new state,
which is the state at time t.
The principle of quantum mechanics
uh that I'm going to say now is first of
all that the evolution is linear. This
can be summarized very easily by saying
that psi of t
is always equal to some linear operator.
I'm going to call it U,
which is a function of time,
times psi of zero.
What is U of time t equals zero? What is
U of zero?
One.
The state psi at time zero is just equal
to the state of psi at time equal to
zero. So, whatever U is, it's equal to
one when t is equal to zero.
But, at some later time, the state
vector is changed and the assumption
Now, this is again one of these things
which is justified by its empirical
success.
All right? It's justified by its
empirical success, but you will see as
we go along
how this connects to other things in
physics and why
why it might be that how we know that
this is true. But let's just take it as
an assumption
that there exists a linear operator
which is dependent on time. It's not
just a fixed linear operator. It evolves
with time, and whatever the state is at
time zero, you hit it with U of T to
find out what it's doing at a later
time.
That's the first principle of time
evolution.
The second principle of time evolution
is that if we have two vectors,
and now I'm writing a bra and a ket,
and we allow them to evolve with time,
both of them,
that the inner product between them is
unchanged with time. In other words,
that it's equal to phi of zero
times psi of zero
for any value of the time.
This is the statement that distinctions
between states
are maintained with time. If they're
orthogonal, it's enough actually just to
know that orthogonal states go to
orthogonal states. From that, you can
prove that inner products uh
uh remain invariant.
But in particular, for example, if phi
and psi are the same,
then this is just a normalization. Phi
phi is just a normalization which we
normally set equal to one.
This is just a statement then if phi is
equal to psi, it's just a statement that
the that the total probability doesn't
change with time. But the normalization
of the state doesn't change with time.
On the other hand, if phi is orthogonal
to psi,
then what it says is that psi and phi
are measurably different.
There's a experiment that you can do to
distinguish them uniquely, and that will
be true either at time If it's true at
time t equals zero, it will continue to
be true at a later time. So, the logical
relations between states stay invariant
with time. That's an assumption, of
course,
but
uh it is true.
All right, let's see what
this condition here, and this is true
for any pair of vectors psi and phi.
Let's see what it says about U.
Okay.
Psi is equal to U of T times psi, but
let's look at the bra vector. What about
the bra vector?
Should I write U here?
U dagger.
Hermitian conjugate.
Remember, when you uh
when you hermitian conjugate or when you
complex conjugate
a
uh an expression, you have to put in the
uh the hermitian conjugate here.
All right, now let's see what happens to
phi times psi. This is equal
Well, it's equal
on the one hand
to phi of zero
U dagger
U
times
psi of zero.
But it's also equal to just phi of zero
And this is presumed to be true for
every vector every pair of vectors psi
of zero and phi of zero.
Well,
if an equation that I won't prove this,
this is more or less obvious.
If an equation like this is true for
every vector every pair of vectors in
the vector space, there's only one
conclusion, and that conclusion is that
U dagger U must be the unit operator.
Okay?
That's that's something easy to prove,
very easy to prove. I'll leave it to you
to prove. Um that if there's an operator
whose
matrix element between any pair of
states
is the same as just the inner product
between those states, it follows that
our operator must be the unit matrix.
So, here's what we learned. We learned
that U dagger U
is equal to one.
Matrices with this property or operators
with this property that the product of
them times their hermitian conjugate
First of all, before we even talk about
that,
if these were just numbers, it would
correspond to a number times its complex
conjugate. If a number times its complex
conjugate is one, what does that say
about the number?
Unit Unit vector.
Or Or it's just one. It's a phase. It's
a pure phase. It's an e to the i theta
of some sort. On the complex plane, it
says that it
uh that it's on the unit circle.
It's unit in length.
All right, it's
uh if U dagger U is equal to one, if it
were a number.
Matrices with this property are called
unitary.
So, one would say that the time
evolution of quantum systems is governed
by unitary operators which depend on
time.
Let's imagine a very small time
interval,
a time interval of magnitude epsilon,
where epsilon is a very small number, so
small that we can ignore the square of
epsilon.
In other words, in our equations, we're
going to retain things just to first
order in epsilon.
And let's see what it says
for a matrix to be um
unitary.
All right, first of all, if T is equal
to zero,
in other words, if epsilon is equal to
zero, epsilon is a little interval of
time,
if epsilon is equal to zero,
then U is equal to one. So, let's write
down U of epsilon.
Epsilon is a small interval of time.
Starts out being one, and then there's
some small correction to it, and that
correction is of order epsilon. Let's
assume it's of order epsilon.
Times some operator, which is the first
order correction.
All right, now I am going to
just to avoid changing definitions in
midstream, I'm going to put a minus sign
here,
but that's purely a definition.
I'm going to call the operator here H.
And I'm also going to put an I here.
This I so far has no special meaning.
Um it's arbitrary. I could absorb it
into the H if I liked, and I could also
absorb the minus sign in, and I could
have just written 1 minus epsilon H, but
for later purposes, I know that I'm
going to want to define
H so that there's an I here and a minus
sign.
The minus sign is completely arbitrary.
The I
is uh is a nice It's a nice definition,
as we'll see.
So, let's see what the condition on H is
for U to be unitary.
Let's write it down. U dagger U Oh, what
is U dagger?
U dagger of epsilon
is equal to one plus I epsilon.
Remember, we have to complex conjugate
everything when we take hermitian
conjugate.
And then we have to write the hermitian
conjugate of H.
The hermitian conjugate of one is just
one.
The hermitian the the complex conjugate
of I epsilon is minus I epsilon, so the
sign changes here, and we substitute for
H, we substitute H dagger.
And now we multiply the two of them,
and eventually use the approximation
that we can ignore epsilon squared and
only keep things to order epsilon.
All right, so the product is one plus I
epsilon H dagger
times
one minus I epsilon H.
What does that have to equal?
Well,
if U is unitary, that has to equal one.
So, let's expand it out.
One.
Now we have one times minus I epsilon H,
minus I epsilon H.
And then we have plus
I epsilon
H dagger.
And then we have something of order
epsilon squared.
Okay?
All of that has to equal one, and we're
going to we're going to ignore epsilon
squared.
Epsilon is so small
that we can ignore it.
We don't want to ignore epsilon. The
reason being that the ones cancel on
both sides.
Okay? The ones cancel on both sides, and
so the leading term is proportional to
epsilon. And what do we get? We get I
epsilon
H dagger
minus H
should be equal to zero.
Or in other words, to leading order in
epsilon
H dagger, the conclusion is that H
dagger equals H.
In other words, H is Hermitian.
H has a name.
It's called the Hamiltonian.
It's Hermitian, so it's an observable.
And the observable that it corresponds
to is the energy of a system.
The eigenvalues of the matrix H are the
energy levels of a system.
Right?
But this was the main point that defined
in this way with the I here
H should be Hermitian.
We can write this another way. Let's
write it another way, the following way.
Let's write psi of epsilon
minus psi of zero. What is that?
Right?
Um
psi of epsilon is 1 minus I epsilon H
times psi of zero
minus psi of zero.
Well, that just means the ones cancel.
Psi of epsilon minus psi of zero is just
equal to minus I epsilon H psi.
It's just the difference between them.
The extra little piece in U that comes
from here.
This is a difference, but let me divide
it now by epsilon.
Divide everything both sides of the
equation by epsilon.
Well,
this looks like the derivative of psi.
Remember that epsilon be very small.
Take the limit that epsilon is very
small now.
This is the difference of something in
epsilon and it's zero divided by
epsilon.
This is the derivative of psi
with respect to epsilon.
Or with respect to T. T is epsilon is
just a small interval of time.
Right?
So, the change in epsilon divided by a
small interval of time, that's the
derivative of the of the state vector
with respect to time is equal
to minus I H on psi.
This tells you how the wave function of
a system or how the state vector of a
system, I should say how it changes with
time.
H being Hermitian guarantees that U
is unitary. If it's unitary, it
guarantees that the logical relations
between states are maintained with time.
And this is the this is the equation
which governs the evolution of every
quantum system.
Of course, you may get to pick what H
is. I haven't told you what H is.
H may depend on the particular setup.
For example, H may depend on the
magnitude of a magnetic field. It could
depend on all kinds of things. The only
thing we learn from general principles
is that the Hamiltonian should be a
Hermitian operator.
A Hermitian operator has eigenvalues and
eigenvectors.
And the eigenvalues are called the
energy levels.
So, this is the way
a state vector changes with time.
In principle, H can be a function of
time.
For example, if you have an electron in
a magnetic field and you change the
magnetic field.
But if you have a situation where
nothing is changing, magnetic field or
whatever it happens that's governing the
system
happens to be time independent, under
that circumstance H is simply a
fixed definite matrix, a fixed definite
operator
that is called the Hamiltonian.
Any questions?
So, so far
can I conclude that if two things are
entangled, they're going to stay
entangled?
Uh
Not really, no.
No. No.
No.
The only way No. No. No. No. No. No. No.
Um
No.
No, the only thing you can conclude is
if you have two different state vectors,
the inner product of them remains
invariant with time. Now, that's not
that that's that's doesn't tell you that
entanglement
um
uh
No.
That is that is not correct that the two
things. If it were correct
you would not be able to entangle one
thing with another.
If they were unentangled, they would
remain unentangled. And measurements
could not be done.
Right? So, no, that that does not
follow.
Um
Well, then
do we have a a unit for entanglement,
some way Yeah, the entropy.
That is the That's the unit of
entanglement.
Is what? Joules. No. Oh, no. No. No. No.
No. En- entropy
Okay.
Entropy is a pure number.
It's a state description. It describes
the set relationships and it has no No
dimensions. No dimensions. It's measured
in bits.
It's measured in bits, but bits are
measured in units of log 2 or something.
Right? No. No. No. Okay. Um
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Uh no. Um all
right. So, let's let's let's go through
units. Uh the standard thermodynamic
units The standard thermodynamics, let's
write it the thermodynamic equation.
Here's a thermodynamic equation.
The differ- differential change in the
energy in the heat of a system is the
temperature times uh
uh dS, but let's see. We usually put a K
in there or not?
No, no K in there, right?
Ah, no.
Now, what are the units of temperature?
Well, okay, degrees usually, but let's
write another equation. Another equation
would be for the fact that the kinetic
energy of a particle
uh kinetic energy of a particle in a gas
is 3/2
uh K, which is Boltzmann's constant
times the temperature.
So, the temperature always has units of
energy. Temperature has units of energy
divi- energy divided by Boltzmann's
constant, whatever the units of
Boltzmann's constant are. I mean, that
the units of Boltzmann's constant are
energy divided by temperature.
Right?
Right. But
But all But you know, the only reason
that there was this stupid Boltzmann
constant in physics is because people
measured temperature
uh with a stupid thermometer that they
bought in a hardware store.
Okay.
This
The natural real units for temperature
are energy.
Get rid of the Boltzmann constant.
It's just a conversion factor from units
of energy to units of Celsius or
whatever.
Uh
Once you make Once you just get rid of
the Boltzmann constant and say
temperature is measured in units of
energy
then
energy energy dimensionless.
Entropy becomes dimensionless and
entropy
Why is it dimensionless? It's the
logarithm of an integer. How could it
have dimensions? Of course, you you you
assigned it the dimensions of bits, but
a bit is just a meaning a you know, a
unit the dimensionless unit unit.
So,
entropy
is dimensionless
unless you want to put back the
Boltzmann constant and then
and then where does it go? I I can't
figure out where it goes.
Uh Then it's energy per temperature.
If energy divided by temperature in
either case
but uh
Yeah.
Yeah. But for our our purposes, we want
to define entropy in an information
theoretic way.
Uh and all information theorists would
call entropy absolutely dimensionless.
Uh
It's only when they want to connect it
to thermodynamics and then use for the
unit of temperature a thermometer that
uh that Boltzmann's constant enters into
the story.
You know, I don't think Boltzmann ever
knew his own constant, incidentally.
It wasn't until Einstein in 1905 that uh
that Boltzmann's constant was actually
measured. Einstein figured it out.
I had to measure it. Um and Boltzmann
committed suicide the year before
because he was very discouraged because
nobody knew what his constant was.
It's one of the one of the real sad
stories of physics.
Shouldn't make fun of Boltzmann.
He was a very great physicist.
Um
Where are we?
Yeah, let
I'll tell you what I'm going to jump. I
was going to I was going to talk about
the eigenvalues of H, but I'll do that
next time.
Um
And they are of course just called the
energies, the energy levels.
Say that's the
only way you can you can tell us why the
the relationship between H is related to
energy or
It's just called that.
Why? Because it's conserved.
Okay, let's
All right, it it goes It goes back to
Einstein.
Well, everything goes back to Einstein.
That's that doesn't say anything.
Okay.
You know that the way the wave function
varies with time is with an exponential
phase that depends on energies.
And that's that's E equals H new, right?
Oh, there should be a there should be a
Planck's constant in here if I really
want to keep track of um
of uh
uh where does the Planck's constant go
here?
Uh I think the no
Right?
Yeah.
Is the Planck's constant in the So,
let's let's put the Planck's constant
here. I think there's a 2 pi in there or
something like that.
No, there's no 2 pi in there.
It the 2 pi is depending on whether you
use H or H bar.
And with H bar uh there's no 2 pi in
there.
No, it's H bar I over H bar. What's
that? It's H bar I over H bar, right?
Well, that cancels out, so it can't be
over H bar. So
Wait, wait wait a second.
Are you saying it's over H bar?
That makes sense.
Yeah.
Uh yes, it's it's over uh sorry um
uh
d by dt
Yeah, it's over H bar.
Over H bar.
Yeah.
Yeah, energy levels are very small
things in quantum mechanics.
And uh you divide by H bar to find out
how the system changes with time.
Okay, um
good.
Let's
Let's uh suppose that psi
is an eigenvector of H.
H on psi
is equal
uh let me call it omega. If it comes out
to really be omega, I'll be very happy.
Let's call it omega on psi.
Omega being
No.
Energy, E, energy, E for energy.
E is a number.
Psi is an eigenvector of H with
eigenvalue E. Okay?
Just assume.
That means
I'm getting tired. I'm beginning to
fade.
Um
If psi is initially an eigenvector of
energy, it will remain an eigenvector of
energy for all time.
Let's see if we can solve
this equation Let's see if we can solve
this equation assuming that psi remains
an eigenvector of the energy for all
time. Okay. Now, if it remains an
eigenvector of the energy for all time,
you say, "Wait a minute. Wait a minute.
That means it doesn't change."
If it doesn't change,
this is nonsense.
No.
Psi is an eigenvector, but remember that
you can multiply an eigenvector by a
number, in particular a complex number,
and it still remains an eigenvector.
So, let's write that psi
of t
is equal
to
a function of time
times psi of zero.
If
psi of zero is an eigenvector of the
energy, so will f of t times psi be an
eigenvector of energy, and therefore so
will the left-hand side. It'll be the
eigenvector with the same eigenvalue.
It'll just be multiplied. And let's see
if we can solve this by seeing if we can
find an f of t which will allow this to
be solved. Okay, so what does it say? We
just factor out psi of zero, and what it
says is that the f of t
by dt
is equal to minus I.
Now, H on psi gives E times psi. So,
that gives an E
divided by H bar times f all multiplying
the vector psi.
But we can divide We can just get rid of
the vector psi
at time t equals zero.
This equation just becomes an equation
for the function f of t.
The f by dt is minus I E over H bar f.
All I've done is substitute for psi of t
f of t times psi of zero
and then used that H on psi over here is
E times psi.
You know how to solve this?
The solution of an equation like this
is just that f
goes like E to the minus I E over H bar
t.
times f of zero.
So, what it says is if you start with an
eigenvector of the energy or eigenvector
of the Hamiltonian,
then it evolves with time just by
multiplying by a time-dependent phase.
That's all that happens.
Okay? What do you call a coefficient in
an E to the I something t? What do you
call a coefficient of t?
Well, no, it's usually called a time
constant if it's real.
Then it would be the K constant. You
call it the frequency.
You call it the Not the frequency, but
the uh the angular frequency, omega.
So,
we have that the wave function evolves
with a frequency with an angular
frequency omega, which is equal to the
energy over H bar, or better yet, energy
is H bar times omega.
That should be a familiar equation.
It also can be written energy is
ordinary frequency times uh
times uh
Planck's original constant.
It differs by factor of 2 pi.
I'm getting tired, and my cold is
getting worse and worse. So, we're going
to quit now. But I thought I would just
show you this, and we'll come back to
it. But the um
phases and the fact that frequency is
related to energy
is equivalent to this equation, which
tells you how states change with time.
This equation also has a name.
The name is the Schrödinger equation.
This is the Schrödinger equation. It's
not the particular Schrödinger equation
that Schrödinger wrote down for a
particular free particle.
That was a particle in a potential. That
was a special case of this. This is the
generalized Schrödinger equation for any
system, but you have to pick a
Hamiltonian.
We'll do some of that next time. We'll
pick out some examples, again, particle
in a magnetic field or other examples
like that.
The preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.